A Register of the W. Langhorne Bond Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
W. Langhorne Bond Papers
1930-1998
2005C58
Bond, W. Langhorne, 1893-1985.
4 manuscript boxes (1.6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers describe China during the period surrounding World War II and the Chinese Revolution. The documents, including correspondence, reports, writings, printed matter, personal documents, and photographs, contain descriptions, observations, and insights about political events in East Asia especially during the Sino-Japanese War and World War II. A majority of the material is documentation about the China National Aviation Corporation.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2005.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biography Note
1893 November 12 Born William Langhorne in Petersburg, Virginia, son of Thomas Baker Bond, a tobacco buyer, and Mary Potter Langhorne
1917 Enlisted in World War I, serving in the army in France for the duration of the war
1929 Started working for Curtiss-Wright Corporation
1931 Accepted the position of Operations Manager for the China National Aviation Corporation (CNAC), in Shanghai
1933 When Pan American Airways purchased Curtiss-Wright interests in CNAC, Bond became a Pan American employee
1935 May 15 Married Katherine (Kitsi) Dunlop in Shanghai
1937 When fighting broke out between Japan and China, Pan American withdrew from active operations in China during the United States policy of political neutrality. Bond became a CNAC employee to ensure the continued operations of CNAC as a Chinese civilian air transport company. After the war, he returned to work for Pan American
1937-1942 CNAC continued to be active through the war despite evacuations from the main operating bases of Shanghai, Hankow and Hong Kong
1941 Pioneered the "Hump" route between China and India, an essential air link to China during World War II
1947 Promoted to vice president, Orient by Pan American Airlines
1949 After the fall of the Nationalist Chinese government, CNAC assets were sold to China for the Civil Air Transport
1950 Retired to his farm in Warrenton, Virginia
1985 July 16 Died, Ponte Vedra, Florida
2001 Author, Wings for an Embattled China, ed. James E. Ellis, Lehigh University Press, 2001. Posthumously published autobiography and history of the CNAC
Scope and Content of Collection
Acquired by the Hoover Institution in 2005, the W. Langhorne Bond papers describe China during the period surrounding World War II and the Chinese Revolution. The documents contain descriptions, observations, and insights about political events in East Asia during the time. A majority of the material is documentation of the China National Aviation Corporation (CNAC).
CNAC was first established as a cooperative company by the Curtiss-Wright Corporation and the Chinese Government. The American interest in the company, known as China Federal Airways, was purchased by Pan American Airways in 1933. Bond, known to most as "Bondy," began as operations manager for the company in 1931 and continued to work for the company until his retirement from the post of Pan American's vice president, Orient in 1950.
CNAC provided passenger, freight, and mail services to the Chinese Nationalist government. The small but effective airline was active during World War II, even as the Japanese took over large segments of China. The materials in the collection document events such as the evacuation of Hong Kong and a CNAC plane shot down by the Japanese. Bond also pioneered the "Hump" route over the Himalayas from China to India in 1941, which brought necessary supplies to the Chinese during the war. Prints in the Photographs document the first flight over the "Hump."
Materials documenting the operations of CNAC may be found in the Correspondence series. Of note is correspondence between Bond and other Pan American employees including H. M. Bixby, a Pan American vice president in China and the Philippines, and S. E. Morgan, a corporation general purchasing agent in New York. However, most CNAC correspondence before 1937 was lost when moved from Shanghai to Hankow after the outbreak of war with the Japanese. Additional information on the overall history of CNAC may be found in materials the Writings series, as well as the CNAC Files.
Images of the CNAC Staff, airplanes, airports, the Bond family, and travel in China during the 1930s and 1940s are found in the Photographs.
Wings for an Embattled China, By W. Langhorne Bond, ed. James E. Ellis, published by Lehigh University Press in 2001 is an autobiography of Bond and overall history of CNAC.
Throughout the collection description, the Romanization of Chinese place names have been kept as they were spelled by Bond in the 1930s and 1940s.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: Biographical File, Correspondence, Writings, China National Aviation Corporation (CNAC) Files, Photographs, and Printed Materials
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
China National Aviation Corporation.; Pan American Airways Corporation.; Aeronautics--China.; Sino-Japanese Conflict, 1937-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--China.; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations.; World War, 1939-1945--Transportation.
Container List
- Biographical File, 1936-1982, undated.
  Includes identification cards, clippings, and articles. Arranged by document type, then chronologically.
  - Biography and identification cards, undated, 1936-1940 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Clippings, 1947; 1982, undated (Folder 1: 2)
  - "New Horizons", article on evacuation of Hong Kong, 1942 (Folder 1: 3)
- Correspondence, 1929-1984.
  Includes both personal and CNAC business correspondence, containing descriptions of life, business and politics in China, particularly during World War II. Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - General, 1938-1982 (Folder 1: 4)
  - American Consular Service, 1937-1945 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Bixby, H. M., 1937-1950 (Folder 1: 7-11)
  - Bond, Kisti, 1937-1948 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Bond, Mary (mother), 1937 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Brock, Horace, 1977 (Folder 1: 14)
  - China National Aviation Corporation (CNAC), 1929-1949 (Folder 1: 15-17)
  - Soong Ching Ling, 1942, 1950 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Leary, William (Bill), 1969-1979 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Morgan, S. W., 1937-1940 (Folder 1: 20, Box-folder 2: 1-2)
  - Mulroney, J. D., 1970 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Neumann, Gerhard, 1971, 1983 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Pan American Airways, 1937-1950 (Folder 2: 5)
  - United States Armed Forces, 1937, 1942 (Folder 2: 6)
  - United States Embassy, Chungking and Hankow, 1938-1939 (Folder 2: 7)
- Writings, 1965; 1972, undated.
  Consists of histories of the CNAC. Arranged chronologically by date of publication.
  - CNAC Chronology, undated. (Folder 2: 8)
    Typescript
  - History of the CNAC, undated. (Folder 2: 9)
  - Operating History of the CNAC, undated. (Folder 2: 10)
  - Wings for an Embattled China, Chapter 6, undated. (Folder 2: 11)
  - Handwritten chapter drafts, undated (Folder 2: 12)
  - Deposition, John Costello v. Pan American World Airways, 1965. (Folder 2: 13)
    Concerning the 1949 evacuations of refugees
  - Wings over Asia; A brief history of CNAC, by CNAC Foundation, 1972. (Folder 2: 14)
    Printed copy
- China National Aviation Corporation (CNAC) Files, 1930-1947.
  Brochures, contracts and reports describing CNAC operations. Arranged by document type. Additional information on the company may be found in the Correspondence and Writings series.
  - Brochures, circa 1930 (Folder 2: 15)
  - Contracts
    - Ministry of Communications and Directorate of Posts, National Government, Republic of China, 1930 (Folder 2: 16)
    - Pan American Airways, circa 1933 (Folder 2: 17)
    - National Government, Republic of China, 1933 (Folder 2: 18)
    - National Government, Republic of China, American Armed Forces, 1947 (Folder 2: 19)
  - Report on air freight service to China, 1941 (Folder 2: 20)
- Photographs, 1935-1949, undated.
  Photographic prints of Bond, his family, homes, travels, and CNAC operations. Photographs identify CNAC planes, airports, routes, and events. Arranged by subject.
  - W. L. Bond and Kitsi Bond, undated; 1938, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Groups with W. L. and Kitsi Bond, undated; 1938, 1942 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Homes
    - Shanghai apartment, 2030 Joffre, 1935 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Shanghai house, 279 Route Charles Culty, 1937. (Folder 3: 4)
      Includes baby Langhorne
    - Repulse Bay cottage, Hong Kong, 1938 (Folder 3: 5)
  - Travel
    - Chinese scenes, undated. (Folder 3: 6)
      Unidentified
    - Photographic post cards, undated (Folder 3: 7)
    - Calcutta, undated (Folder 3: 8)
    - Japan, undated (Folder 3: 9)
    - Nanking, undated (Folder 3: 10)
    - Shanghai, undated (Folder 3: 11)
    - Houkow flood, 1931 (Folder 3: 12)
    - Great Wall of China trip from Peking, 1935 (Folder 3: 13)
    - Chungking, 1936 (Folder 3: 14)
    - Hangchow Bore, undated, 1936 (Folder 3: 15)
    - Yangtze River trip, 1936 (Folder 3: 16-17)
    - En Route to Hong Kong, Repulse Bay Hotel, 1940 (Folder 3: 18)
  - CNAC
    - Airplanes, undated. (Folder 3: 19)
      Includes CNAC staff and a Sikorsky helicopter
    - Airports: Lunghwa, Shanghai, and Kai Tak, Hong Kong, undated (Folder 3: 20)
    - Staff, undated (Folder 3: 21)
    - New office, Peking, undated (Folder 3: 22)
    - War scenes, undated (Folder 3: 23)
    - Airplanes, street scenes, and damage photographed by Captain Higgins, undated. (Folder 3: 24)
      Printed 35mm film proofs
    - Airplane piloted by Captain H. L. Woods shot down by Japanese, 1938 (Folder 3: 25)
    - First survey flight over the "Hump" from Linking, China to Dinjin, India, 1941 (Folder 3: 26)
    - Twentieth anniversary staff photo, 1949 (Folder 3: 27)
- Printed Materials, 1935-1998, undated.
  Clippings and published materials. Arranged chronologically.
  - General brochures and pamphlets, undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Curtiss-Wright Corporation brochure featuring CNAC, undated. (Folder 4: 2)
    In Chinese
  - Pan American Airways Flying Clipper Ships map, undated (Folder 4: 3)
  - A Pictorial Map of Peiping, undated (Folder 4: 4)
  - Clippings, 1935-1953, undated (Folder 4: 5-9)
  - Peking Utility Book, Peking International Women's Club, 1934-1935 (Folder 4: 10)
  - Handbook of the American University Club, Shanghai, 1935 (Folder 4: 11)
  - Who's Who in China, 5th edition, The China Weekly Review, 1936 (Folder 4: 12)
  - War Messages and Other Selections, Madame Chiang Kai-shek, 1938. (Folder 4: 13)
    Inscribed by author
  - "Inside Story of a Japanese Peace Overture to China during the Second World War," Chin-chao Liang, published in Cheung Chi Journal, 1974. (Folder 4: 14)
  - Clipper newsletter, Pan Am Historical Foundation, 1997-1998 (Folder 4: 15)